Cyndy Szekeres Papers 1997.0078
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Cyndy Szekeres Papers
1961-2004.
1997.0078
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
56.25 Linear feet
Cyndy Szekeres has illustrated over 40 children's books, and is best known for her animal characters.
Szekeres, Cyndy.
Biography
Cyndy Szekeres (pronounced "zeck-er-es") was born 31 October 1933, the daughter of a toolmaker, Stephen Szekeres, and his wife Anna Ceplousky Szekeres. In 1954, Szekeres earned a certificate from the Pratt Institute in New York. Szekeres has illustrated over 40 children's books, and is best known for her animal characters. She has also written or compiled and self-illustrated 67 titles. Szekeres won the AIGA Award for her work on Moon Mouse (1969). Szekeres currently lives on a farm in Vermont.
Scope and Content
The Cyndy Szekeres Papers consist mainly of correspondence, artwork, and publishing materials for over two dozen Cyndy Szekeres titles, dating from 1961 to the 1980s. The collection also includes pieces from later dates. The collection includes both preliminary and finished artwork, dummies, separations, and proofs, as well as typescripts for select titles.
Arrangement
The collection contains a single series, arranged alphabetically by book title. Materials are boxed together according to size, but listed in the finding aid according to title.
Series I: children's Literature ( undated, 1961-2004 ) is arranged alphabetically by title.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
The 329th Friend Dodd Call No. CLC C3654
ABC, 123 Dodd Call No. CLC 361
ABC Picture Alphabet for Use Ones Dodd Call No. CLC D367
All By Himslef Dodd Call No. CLC 1867
Animal ABC Book Dodd Call No. CLC C1907
Animal Antics Dodd Call No. WPZ 149
Animal and Bird in Picture and Word Dodd Call No. CLC D3640
Animal Children: the Friends of the Forest and the Plain Dodd Call No. CLC C999
Animal Friends Dodd Call No. CLC C1896
The Animal Story Book Dodd Call No. CLC A790
Animals I Know Dodd Call No. CLC D368
Art in the Nursery Dodd Call No. CLC A785
Argentaybee and the Boonies Dodd Call No.
Baby Animals and Birds Dodd Call No. CLC D369
Baby's First Book Dodd Call No. CLC D370
Baby Picture Primer Dodd Call No. CLC C1894
Bashful Ballads Dodd Call No. CLC A787
The Bashful Earthquake & Other Fables and Verses Dodd Call No. CLC A808
Beasts of the Field Dodd Call No. CLC A811
Bible ABC Book Dodd Call No. CLC C1898
Bird Stories for Little People Dodd Call No. CLC C1883
Black Beauty Dodd Call No. Black Beauty 448
Bonny Birds Dodd Call No. CLC C1888
Book of Cats and Dogs Dodd Call No. CLC A789
Book of Humor Dodd Call No. CLC 1886
A Book of Kitties Dodd Call No. CLC D363
Bounce, the Study of a Kitten Dodd Call No. CLC C1881
Bunny Babies Dodd Call No. CLC C1895
Brian's Secret Errand Dodd Call No.
Brimhall Comes to Stay Dodd Call No. CLC B126
Careless Jane, and Other Tales Dodd Call No. CLC A805
A Christmas Party Dodd Call No. CLC C3644
Goodbye, Hello Dodd Call No. A 2329
Good Night Orange Monster Dodd Call No. CLC C3642
Great Grandmother Cat Tales Dodd Call No. CLC A2171
Gus and Buster Work Things Out Dodd Call No. CLC A2328
The Hollow Tree Dodd Call No. CLC B511, CLC A2144, Babbidge Library PZ 10 .3 P16 Ha
Hurray for Pippa! Dodd Call No. CLC A2325
Little Chick's Story Dodd Call No. CLC A2322
Little Richard Dodd Call No. CLC A2320
Macaroni Dodd Call No. CLC C3640
Maybe, a Mole Dodd Call No. CLC A2323
More about Waggy Dodd Call No. CLC A2319
Mrs. Updaisy Dodd Call No. CLC A2321
Mystery in the Night Woods Dodd Call No. CLC A2326
My Workbook Diary Dodd Call No. CLC C3645
Night Noises and other Mole and Troll stories Dodd Call No. CLC C3646
No! No! Dodd Call No. CLC A2522
Pippa Pops Out! Dodd Call No. CLC A2324
The Snowed-In Book Dodd Call No. CLC B383/A2381
Waggy and his Friends Dodd Call No. CLC A2318
Walter, the lazy mouse Dodd Call No. CLC C3643
What Can You Do Without a Place to Play Dodd Call No. CLC C3641
Who Will Believe Tom Kitten? Dodd Call No. CLC A2327
The Workbook Diary Dodd Call No. CLC C3645
3 photographs.
1 audiotape.
Bibliography
Acquisition Information
The collection has been donated by the artist in installments beginning in 1991.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of children's literature and artwork. Several of these collections, such as the Richard Scarry Papers, the Ruth Krauss Papers, the Leonard Everett Fisher Papers, and the Joseph A. Smith Papers, present the work of children's authors/illustrators active during the same periods as Szekeres. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Bailey, Carolyn Sherwin.; Berends, Polly B.; Boegehold, Betty.; Bourne, Miriam Anne.; Bronin, Andrew.; Coward, McCann, and Geoghegan, Inc.; Cunningham, Julia.; Flack, Marjorie.; Hiller, Catherine.; Hitte, Katherine.; Holl, Adelaide.; Johnston, Tony.; Kwitz, Mary DeBall.; Lampman, Evelyn Sibley.; Latham, Jean.; Lewi, Bee.; Lifton, Betty Jean.; Lombardo, Katherine.; Lonergan, Joy.; Lystad, Mary.; Myller, Lois.; Ormondroyd, Edward.; Paine, Albert Bigelow.; Parrish, Peggy.; Peterson, John.; Random House, Inc.; Robinson, Barbara.; Scarry, Patricia M.; Scarry, Patsy.; Sharmat, Marjorie Weinam.; Szekeres, Cyndy.; Vaughhan, Sam.; Wahl, Jan.; Welber, Robert.; Artist.; Audio cassettes.; Author.; Books.; Children's artists.; Children's illustration.; Children's literature.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Illustrations (visual works).; Illustrator.; Manuscripts.; Northeast Children's Literature Collection.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Press releases.; Publications.; Sketches.; Sound recordings.; Typescripts.; Works of Art.
- Series I: Children's Literature, undated, 1961-2004
  - The 329th Friend
    - Original artwork, title page-page 25, ca. 1979 (Box 6:, Folder 65)
    - Original artwork, pages 26-48, ca. 1979 (Box 6:, Folder 66)
    - Oversize artwork (pages 10-11, 20-23, 28-29, 36-45), ca. 1979 (Box 31:, Folder 132)
  - Argentaybee and the Boonie
    - Correspondence, 1977 February - 1981 November (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Notes, undated (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Layout sketches, ca. 1979 (Box 6:, Folder 67)
    - Preliminary sketches, ca. 1979 (Box 6:, Folder 68)
    - Cover mock-up, ca. 1979 (Box 31:, Folder 133)
    - Illustrated paste-up dummy, ca. 1979 (Box 31:, Folder 134)
    - Cover artwork, ca. 1979 (Box 31:, Folder 135)
    - Original artwork (pages 1-18; 9 pieces), ca. 1979 (Box 31:, Folder 136)
    - Original artwork (pages 19-32; 8 pieces), ca. 1979 (Box 31:, Folder 137)
  - Brian's Secret Errand
    - Mock-up and copy, ca. 1969 (Box 6:, Folder 69)
    - Overlays (cover to page 19), ca. 1969 (Box 32:, Folder 138)
    - Overlays (pages 20-44), ca. 1969 (Box 32:, Folder 139)
      General note
      Pages 22-23 missing.
  - Bush Gallery Art Show, undated (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - A Christmas Party
    - Magazine excerpt, ca. 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Original artwork (10 pieces), ca. 1975 (Box 6:, Folder 70)
  - Did You Ever? Never! [unpublished]
    - Original artwork (8 pieces), early 1960s (Box 7:, Folder 71)
      [Date per Szekeres.]
  - Edgemont
    - Correspondence, 1975 December - 1976 February (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - Photographs and clippings (copies), ca. 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Partial dummy, ca. 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, ca. 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Jacket plan, ca. 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Preliminary sketches, ca. 1976 (Box 7:, Folder 72)
    - Overlays (20 pieces), ca. 1976 (Box 32:, Folder 140)
  - The Fattest Bear in the First Grade
    - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - Proofs, ca. 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - Sketches (2 pieces), ca. 1969 (Box 24:, Folder 104)
    - Overlays (17 pieces), ca. 1969 (Box 24:, Folder 105)
    - Uncut proof sheet, ca. 1969 (Box 33:, Folder 141)
  - Four-Ring Three
    - Correspondence, 1972 March - May (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Original artwork, dust jacket (4 pieces), ca. 1972 - 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Paste-up dummy and copy [FRAGILE], ca. 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Plans for cover, ca. 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Sketches (9 pieces), ca. 1972-73 (Box 7:, Folder 73)
    - Overlays (cover, pages 1-47), ca. 1973 (Box 8)
    - Dust jackets, ca. 1973 (Box 33:, Folder 142)
  - Good Night, Orange Monster
    - Overlays (cover, pages 2-40), ca. 1972 (Box 24:, Folder 107)
  - Goodbye, Hello
    - Sketches, ca. 1974 (Box 7:, Folder 74)
    - Overlays with note by Szekeres (18 pieces), ca. 1974 (Box 24:, Folder 106)
  - Great Grandmother Cat Tales
    - Jacket proof, ca. 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Artwork (pages 3-5, 12-51, 54-57, endpapers, back cover, and small art), ca. 1976 (Box 9)
    - Dummy page (1 piece), ca. 1976 (Box 24:, Folder 108)
  - Gus and Buster Work Things Out
    - Preliminary sketches (2 pieces), ca. 1975 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
    - Partial paste-up dummy and copy, ca. 1975 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
    - Artwork (cover-page 64), ca. 1975 (Box 10)
    - Dust jackets, ca. 1975 (Box 24:, Folder 109)
  - Halloween Parade
    - Contract (incomplete), ca. 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
    - Jacket plans, ca. 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
    - Cover mock-up, ca. 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
    - Proofs (copy 1), 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
    - Proofs (copy 2), 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
    - Partial rough galley, 1973 January 15 (Box 7:, Folder 75)
    - Sketches, ca. 1973 (Box 7:, Folder 76)
    - Overlays (17 pieces), ca. 1973 (Box 33:, Folder 143)
    - Dust jackets (2 pieces), ca. 1973 (Box 33:, Folder 144)
  - Happy Birthday, Mole and Troll
    - Color illustration and copy (2 pieces), 1989 Septmeber (Box 24:, Folder 110)
    - Original artwork (Cover plan, cover art, pages 2-29; 15 pieces), ca. 1989 (Box 25)
    - Original artwork (pages 30-64 and end pages; 14 pieces), ca. 1989 (Box 26)
  - Here's Pippa Again
    - Artwork with overlays (24 pieces), ca. 1989 (Box 33:, Folder 145)
  - Holiday Card Illustration, 2004 (Box 7:, Folder 77)
    [Note: Pippa illustration colorized by Szekeres for the University of Connecticut Libraries and Dodd Center holiday card 2004.]
  - The Hollow Tree (Box :)
    - Sketch dummy, ca. 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - Original artwork (39 pieces), ca. 1973 (Box 7:, Folder 78)
    - Opening pages (2 pieces), ca. 1973 (Box 27:, Folder 111)
  - Hurray for Pippa!
    - Original artwork (28 pieces), ca. 1980 (Box 11)
    - Cover art (1 piece), undated (Box 27:, Folder 112)
  - James the Jaguar
    - Notes, ca. 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 25)
    - Preliminary artwork (2 pieces), ca. 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 26)
    - Dummy, ca. 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 27)
    - Color proofs, ca. 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 28)
    - Unused artwork (2 pieces), ca. 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 29)
    - Photocopy of drawing, ca. 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 30)
    - Sketches, ca. 1972 (Box 27:, Folder 113)
    - Original artwork (15 pieces), ca. 1972 (Box 34 [OS]:)
  - Jumper Goes to School
    - Partial proof, ca. 1969 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
    - Original artwork (13 pieces), ca. 1969 (Box 36:, Folder 150)
  - Ladybug and Dog and the Nightwalk
    - Original artwork (14 pieces), ca. 1980 (Box 27:, Folder 114)
  - Little Chick's Story
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, ca. 1978 (Box 3:, Folder 32)
    - Sample covers from the "Early I Can Read" series, ca. 1978 (Box 3:, Folder 33)
    - Typescripts, ca. 1978 (Box 28:, Folder 119)
    - Dust jacket, ca. 1978 (Box 28:, Folder 120)
    - Cover materials, ca. 1978 (Box 28:, Folder 121)
    - Separations [FRAGILE. Stuck together.], ca. 1978 (Box 28:, Folder 122)
    - Black and white illustrations (17 pieces), ca. 1978 (Box 28:, Folder 123)
    - Text separations, ca. 1978 (Box 28:, Folder 124)
    - Proof page, ca. 1978 (Box 36:, Folder 152)
  - Little Richard
    - Typescript (incomplete), ca. 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 34)
    - Guide to printer's marks, ca. 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 35)
    - Sketches, ca. 1970 (Box 7:, Folder 79)
    - Layout plan, ca. 1970 (Box 7:, Folder 80)
    - Text separations, 1970 (Box 7:, Folder 81)
      Date per original folder.
    - Separations with black and white artwork, ca. 1970 (Box 7:, Folder 82)
    - Separations with color artwork, ca. 1970 (Box 7:, Folder 83)
    - Proof pages, ca. 1970 (Box 7:, Folder 84)
    - Photocopies, ca. 1970 (Box 7:, Folder 85)
  - Little Richard and Prickles (Box :)
    - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 36)
    - Illustration list, 1971 September 7 (Box 3:, Folder 37)
    - Original artwork (endpapers-page 43), ca. 1970-1971 (Box 13)
    - Original artwork (pages 44-end), ca. 1970-1971 (Box 14)
  - Macaroni
    - Separations, ca. 1968 (Box 36:, Folder 151)
  - Maybe, a Mole
    - Correspondence, 1974, 1976 (Box 3:, Folder 38)
    - Typescripts, ca. 1974 (Box 3:, Folder 39)
    - Original black and white artwork (17 pieces, plus letter), ca. 1974 (Box 3:, Folder 40)
    - Sketches (5 pieces), ca. 1974 (Box 7:, Folder 86)
    - Cover artwork and dust jacket (3 pieces), ca. 1974 (Box 27:, Folder 115)
  - Michael the Upstairs Dog
    - Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 4:, Folder 41)
    - Original artwork, ca. 1967 (Box 35:, Folder 146)
  - More about Waggy
    - Notes, ca. 1973 (Box 4:, Folder 42)
    - Layout plans, ca. 1973 (Box 4:, Folder 43)
    - Proofs, ca. 1973 (Box 4:, Folder 44)
    - Cover, ca. 1973 (Box 7:, Folder 87)
    - Black and white separations (25 pieces), ca. 1973 (Box 7:, Folder 88)
    - Color artwork (2 pieces), ca. 1973 (Box 7:, Folder 89)
    - Cover separations, ca. 1973 (Box 35 [OS]:, Folder 147)
  - Mrs. Updaisy
    - Small original artwork (17 pieces), 1963 (Box 15:, Folder 90)
    - Large original artwork (40 pieces), 1963 (Box 27:, Folder 116)
  - My Workbook Diary
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, 1971-1975 (Box 4:, Folder 45)
    - Original artwork (15 pieces), 1971-1975 (Box 12)
    - Black and white artwork (3 pieces), 1971-1975 (Box 15:, Folder 91)
    - Large original artwork (2 pieces), 1971-1975 (Box 15:, Folder 92)
  - Mystery in the Night Woods
    - Original artwork (19 pieces), 1969 (Box 27:, Folder 117)
    - Cover mechanical, ca. 1969 (Box 27:, Folder 118)
  - New Shoes
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 46)
    - Notes, ca. 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 47)
    - Partial typescript, ca. 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 48)
    - Sketches, ca. 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 49)
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, ca. 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 50)
    - Proofs, partial proofs, jacket proofs, ca. 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 51)
    - Advertisement, ca. 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 52)
    - Copies (negative), ca. 1961 (Box 15:, Folder 93)
    - Original artwork (15 pieces), ca. 1961 (Box 29:, Folder 125)
    - Original artwork (4 pieces), ca. 1961 (Box 29:, Folder 126)
    - Paste-up sheet, ca. 1961 (Box 29:, Folder 127)
  - Night Noises and Other Mole and Troll Stories
    - Partial typescript, ca. 1977 (Box 5:, Folder 53)
    - Sketches, ca. 1977 (Box 5:, Folder 54)
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, ca. 1977 (Box 5:, Folder 55)
    - Large sketches (3 pieces), ca. 1977 (Box 15:, Folder 94)
    - Detached black and white separations, ca. 1977 (Box 15:, Folder 95)
    - Detached color separations, ca. 1977 (Box 15:, Folder 96)
    - Art and text separations (pages 1-35), ca. 1977 (Box 16)
    - Art and text separations (36-end), ca. 1977 (Box 17)
    - Original color artwork (2 pieces), ca. 1977 (Box 29:, Folder 128)
    - Cover art with separations, ca. 1977 (Box 29:, Folder 129)
  - No! No!
    - Typescript (copy), 1970 March 6 (Box 5:, Folder 56)
    - Layout sketch, ca. 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 57)
    - Preliminary sketches (8 pieces), ca. 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 58)
    - Dummy [FRAGILE], ca. 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 59)
    - Original artwork (19 pieces), ca. 1971 (Box 15:, Folder 97)
    - Dust jacket, ca. 1971 (Box 15:, Folder 98)
  - Pippa Mouse
    - Preliminary cover art, ca. 1989 (Box 15:, Folder 99)
    - Cover art (1 piece), 1989 (Box 35 [OS]:, Folder 148)
  - Pippa Pops Out
    - Original artwork (27 pieces), ca. 1979 (Box 18)
    - Cover art (1 piece), ca. 1979 (Box 35 [OS]:, Folder 149)
  - Small Clown and Tiger
    - Original artwork (33 pieces), 1967-1968 (Box 30)
    - Separations, ca. 1967-1968 (Box 37 [OS]:, Folder 154)
  - The Snowed-In Book
    - Original artwork (80 pieces), ca. 1974 (Box 19)
  - Unidentified correspondence, undated (Box 5:, Folder 60)
  - Unidentified artwork, undated, 2001 (Box 15:, Folder 100)
  - Unidentified painting, undated (Box 37 [OS]::, Folder 155)
  - Waggy and His Friends
    - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 61)
    - Photocopies of black and white artwork, ca. 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 62)
    - Proofs, ca. 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 63)
    - Black and white artwork separations, ca. 1971 (Box 15:, Folder 101)
    - Black and white separations with text [FRAGILE], ca. 1971 (Box 15:, Folder 102)
    - Color separations, ca. 1971 (Box 20)
    - Small color separations, ca. 1971 (Box 21)
    - Sketches, ca. 1971 (Box 29:, Folder 130)
    - Black and white separations, ca. 1971 (Box 36:, Folder 153)
  - Walter the Lazy Mouse
    - Sketch, undated (Box 5:, Folder 64)
    - Original black and white artwork (34 pieces), ca. 1963 (Box 22)
  - What Can You Do Without a Place to Play?
    - Black and white separtions (20 pieces), ca. 1971 (Box 37:, Folder 156)
    - Color separations (22 pieces), ca. 1971 (Box 38)
  - When Homer Honked
    - Color artwork (1 piece), ca. 1961 (Box 15:, Folder 103)
    - Original black and white artwork (9 pieces), ca. 1961 (Box 29:, Folder 131)
  - Who Will Believe Tom Kitten?
    - Original black and white artwork (28 pieces), ca. 1978 (Box 23)
- Series II: Audiovisual materials
  - "Cyndy Szekeres Talks about Herself", 1990 (Cassette 1997-0078/AC1)